Guide to the Ernest G. Sihler Papers 1872 - 1934 MC 67
New York University Archives
Ernest G. Sihler Papers
1872-1934
MC 67
New York University Archives
13.0 linear feet
The Ernest G. Sihler Papers consist of notebooks and other materials generated by Classicist and New York University Latin Professor Ernest G. Sihler (1853-1942). The collection is made up primarily of notebooks containing handwritten notes on Classical subjects made to augment Sihler's scholarship and teaching; the notebooks are often written in a combination of English, Latin, and Ancient Greek, and his earliest student notebooks are in German. The collection also contains manuscripts and a small amount of correspondence.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Some of the notebooks are in poor condition with decaying or missing bindings. A few of the notebooks have been temporarily removed for conservation to the Bobst Library's Preservation Lab.
Biographical Note
Ernest G. Sihler was born in 1853, in Fort Wayne, Indiana, one of nine children. His father, Wilhelm von Sihler (born in Silesia in 1801), had studied to become a lecturer in Modern Literature, but after teaching for a short time in Dresden and Riga chose to become a Lutheran pastor. He then immigrated to the United States in 1843 to serve as a missionary to Germans who had settled in the Midwest; in 1846 he married Susannah Kern and took over the directorship of the Theological Seminary in Fort Wayne. Ernest Sihler attended the Concordia Gymnasium of Fort Wayne, a Lutheran School of the German model, where he studied Latin, Greek and the Classics. He continued his studies at the Divinity School at St. Louis from 1869 to 1872, but decided to pursue a career in the Classics rather than Theology. He studied Classical Philology at the University of Berlin and the University of Leipzig from 1872 to 1875, and was a Fellow in Greek at John Hopkins University from 1876 to 1879, receiving a Ph.D. in 1878. In 1879 Sihler moved to New York City, where he taught at the Dr. Sachs Collegiate Institute and worked as a tutor. He married Emily Birkner in 1881. In 1891 he returned to the Midwest to teach at Concordia College in Milwaukee for one year, returning to New York in 1892 to take a professorship in Latin at New York University, where he remained until 1923. He died in New York in 1942.
Scope and Content Note
The Ernest G. Sihler Papers consist primarily of notes taken by Sihler in the course of his scholarship and teaching. Most of the notes were handwritten in bound notebooks, although some materials were bound after the fact. The notebooks are written in Latin, English, and Ancient Greek, with the earliest written in German. The collection also contains a small amount of visual material (photographs and copies of Sihler's drawings), manuscripts, correspondence, and student work.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in rough chronological order.
Physical Access
Please note that this collection is stored offsite, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Access Restrictions
Materials designated under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. This collection is in
off-site storage
New York University.
- Notebooks and Bound Volumes
  - Berlin - Lectures on Tacitus Agricola, 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Roemische Litteratur, 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aristophanes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Plato - Pindar (Germany) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - George Curtius - Lectures on Greek Grammar (Leipzig), 1874-1875 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lesingii and Libellum, October 1874 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Omnigena (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Leipzig Notebook, 1874-1875 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Index Rerum Philologicarum, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notes on History/Plato's Style (John Hopkins) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Materials for PhD - Grammar (John Hopkins), 1876-1877 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Materials for PhD - Grammar (John Hopkins) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Monographs, 1875-1926 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Translations of Schwegler History of Greek Philosophy, 1877-1878 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dinarchus and his style, etc., 1883-1885 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lectures: History of Greece in the Fifth Century, 1878-1883 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Latin Lectures on Caesar's Life, NYU, 1884-1885 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Historical Studies in Caesar/ Plutarch (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Cicero - De Inventione, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Gaius on Roman Law, etc., 1880s or 1890s (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous excerpts dealing with Roman writers, etc., 1891 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Aristotle's Politics, etc., 1891-1892 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Latin Grammar Points, 1891-1892 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Middle Ages - Greek History, 1891-1892 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Notebook (Michigan), 1892 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lives of Augustus and Tiberius, 1892-1893 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - English to Latin Dictionary, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sources of the History of Tiberius, 1893-1894 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Augustus Princips, 1894 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Lucan Synonyms, 1894-1895 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - De Rebus Romanus, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Pliny Letters, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Cicero De Officus And Vitae Flavorum, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lectures on Roman Law - NYU, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The Latter Part of the Roman Republic - Senior Courses, 1895-1896 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Galustii ..., 1895-1896 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1. Lucretius 2. Cicero and Lucretius, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Upper Class Works in Latin Prose, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Homer, Aristophanes etc., 1898-1901 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Constitutional History of the Roman Republic, 1897-1898 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Roman History 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Lectures on Roman Literature, University Heights, 1898-1899 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - History of New York University Notes, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - The Satires of Horace, University Heights, 1899 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Matter for Latin Discources, 1899-1900 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Cicero, 1900 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Notes on History of Roman Literature, 1900 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - History of Roman Literature from Augustus, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - In the Era of Diocletian, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Volume, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Cicero's Writings on..., 1901 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Latin Words and Word Formations, 1901 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Servius. Latin Rhetoric., n.d. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Plautus II, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Works and Age of Tacitus, 1903-1904 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Classical Literature etc., 1903-1905 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Studies, Chiefly and the Humanities, 1902-1904 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Ledger, 1904-1920 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Ledger Papers, 1909-1920 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Horace, Graduate Course, 1905 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Ode to the President, by Edoardo San Giovanni, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Juvenal, etc., 1905 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Spiritual Elements of Classic Literature, 1905 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Studies Connected with Testimonium Amanae - Index, 1908 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Virgil and Servius (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Life and Letters of Gaius Julius Caesar II, 1909 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - A Survey of All of Cicero's Orations, 1908-1909 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Studies for Annals of Caesar, 1909 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Life and Letters of Gaius Julius Caesar I (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Roman Literature, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Roman History, 1902-1905 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - De Vita et Rebus Gestis Pompei, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Life and Letters of Gaius Julius Caesar III (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Plautus New Course - Graduate, 1910 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Annals of Caesar, German Edition, 1912 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Annals of Caesar (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - De Catone Censorio, 1911 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Synonyms, 1911 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Annals of Cicero (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Theodor Mommsen, Annals of Cicero (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript of Cicero Appinum, 1913-1914 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Hippocrates and Other Greeks Physicians (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - About Mommsen. Dictionary., 1910 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Cicero of Appinum, 1916 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Vergil, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Imperial History, 1915 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Sourcework on Book, 1916 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Cicero's Consular Election and Consular Years I, 1916 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - History of Roman Literature Supplementary Notes I, 1916 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Latin Lectures to Juniors, Seniors, 1916-1917 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Syllabus of History of Roman Republic, 1917 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Claudius, New, Seneca, 1917 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Cicero's Consular Election and Consular Year II, 1917 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Neoplatonism, 1918 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript of Emperor Julian and His Religion (Written in back of student's notebook), October 1917 - April 1919
  - Tetullian, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - New Testament, Grammar, Symmachus, 1918 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Pliny, Studies fir "From Augustus to Augustine" (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Advanced Course in Latin Writing and Speaking, 1919 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - The Old Believers in Rome, 1919 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Earlier Stages of Augustine, c. 1919 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - A Study of Quintiliian (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Polybins, 1920 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Euesebius and Jerome (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Quintilian of Caliguris - An Essay, 1920 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Later Chapters of "From Augustus to Augustine", 1921 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Justinian and Roman Law, etc., 1921 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - The Last Chapter of "From Augustus to Augustine", 1921 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Cassa (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Notebook, 1925 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Lights and Shadows from Ancient History, and Diogenes Laertus (Lectures), 1925 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - From Maumee to Thames and Tiber (autobiography), 1930 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Herodotus, Translated by E.G. Sihler, 1934-1935 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Aristotle on the State, Translated by E.G. Sihler, 1935 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Pausanias, 1937-1938 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Thucydides, 1936 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - The Works of Xenophin, 1936-1937 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Pausanias, Part II, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Kuebner de Litterus Romanis II, c. 1880s (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Studies in Cicero's Idiom, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - History of the Roman Republic, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Caesariana, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Roman Government - NYU, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Mythus in Plato, etc., n.d. (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Testimonium Animae (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Cicero, etc. (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Journal - General Notes, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 3)
- Manuscripts, Correspondence, and Papers (Box 1)
  - Drawings (copies), n.d. (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - History Synopses - Greek, Middle Ages, 2.0 pages (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1900 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Student Papers, 1921 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1931 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Photographs - For Autobiography (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - From Maumee to Thames and Tiber - unbound manuscript, 1 of 2, 1928 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - From Maumee to Thames and Tiber - unbound manuscript, 2 of 2, 1928 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - From Maumee to Thames and Tiber Photostats (excerpt), 1930 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - From Maumee to Thames and Tiber Photostats (excerpt), 1930 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - From Maumee to Thames and Tiber Photostats (excerpt), 1930 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - From Maumee to Thames and Tiber Photostats (excerpt), 1930 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Chancellor Brown, 1934 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Latin Poetry - Lecture Notes (Box 26, Folder 14)